Guide to the Weston La Barre Papers, 1930-1996 UA.29.02.0070
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Publications, 1931-1993
  - Articles
    - Drug Anthology correspondence circa 1970-1971 (Box 9)
    - Old and New World Narcotics: A Statistical Question and an Ethnological Reply, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Review of Wasson's Soma: Divine Mushroom of Immortality, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Anthropological Perspectives on Sexuality, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Authority, Culture Change and the Courts, 1971-1972 (Box 9)
    - I Narcotici Del Nuevo Mondo Autoctano, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Introduction to Anthropology Today, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Materials for a History of Studies of Crisis Cults: A Bibliographic Essay, 1971 (Box 9)
    - North American Peoples and Cultures 1971 (Box 9)
    - Review of Watson's Proxemic Behavior, 1971 (Box 9)
    - Hallucinogens and the Shamanic Origins of Religion, 1972 (Box 9)
    - Non-domesticated plants: uses in medicine and ritual, 1972 (Box 10)
    - The Development of Mind in Man in Primitive Cultures and Society, 1973 (Box 10)
    - Life Cycle and Initiation Rites, 1973 (Box 10)
    - American Religions, 1974 (Box 10)
    - Biology and Language article, 1974 (Box 10)
    - Comments on de Rios's The Influence of Psychotropic Flora and Fauna on Maya Religion, 1974 (Box 10)
    - Anthropological Perspectives on Hallucination and Hallucinogens, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Foreward to Stein and Hill's The Ethnic Imperative: A Study of the White Ethnic Movement, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Letter to the Editor of the Journal of Psychedielic Drugs, 1977 (Box 10)
    - A Retort Courteous, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Review of Rubin's Cannabis and Culture, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Freudian Biology, Magic, and Religion, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Hysteria and Psychopathy, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Letter to Editor of Journal of Psychohistory, 1978 (Box 10)
    - The Making of Psychological Anthropology, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Psychoanalysis and the Biology of Religion, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Academic Graffiti, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Closed Eyes While Kissing, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Devereux Festschrift, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Foreward to Spiro's Gender and Culture: Kibbutz Women Revisited, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Peyotl and Mescaline, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Psychedelics Galore, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Shamanic Origins of Religion and Medicine, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Comments on Ferro Luzzi's The Female Lingam, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Countertransference and the Beatniks, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Letter to the Editor of Southern Anthropologist, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Preface to Devereux's De L'Augoisse A La Methode, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Three Contributions to the Delinquency of Science and Literature, 1980 (Box 10)
    - 'Tribe-Oriented' Anthropologists Missing the Larger Point? 1980 (Box 10)
    - Two Etymons and a Query, 1982-1984 (Box 10)
    - Ethnobotony in American Anthropology, 1983-1987 (Box 10)
    - Charley Charcoal: the Autobiogrpahy of a Kiowa Indian correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 10)
    - A Job on Blow, circa 1985 (Box 10)
    - Mozart's 'Magic Flute' as a Parable of Normal Adolescence, 1985 (Box 10)
    - George Devereux: In Memoriam, 1987 (Box 10)
    - Neoteny and Religion, circa 1987 (Box 10)
    - My Friend Gordon, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Old and New World Hallucinogens, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Importance of Ethnobotany in American Anthropology, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Aymara Texts, undated (Box 10)
    - Lecturer's Reply to Discussants (La Barre's reply to Schlesinger), undated (Box 10)
  - Books
    Books are arranged in alphabetical order because many of La Barre's books were revised and reprinted over a period of years.
    - The Aymara Indians of the Lake Titicaca Plateau, Bolivia, American Anthropological Association, 1948 (Box 10)
    - Culture in Context: Selected Writings of Weston La Barre
      - First edition, Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press, 1980 (Box 10)
      - Notes and Correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 10)
    - The Ghost Dance
      - First edition, Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday & Company, Inc., 1970 (Box 10)
      - Unused Chapters
        - Chapter 7, Death in the Old Stone Age (Box 10)
        - Chapter 8, The Seat of Life (Box 10)
        - Chapter 9, The Immortal One (Box 10)
        - Chapter 14, The Beast God (Box 10)
        - Chapter 15, The Totemic Gods (Box 10)
        - Chapter 16, The Dying God (Box 11)
        - Chapter 17, The Battle of the Gods (Box 11)
        - Chapter 18, The Murdered God (Box 11)
        - Paul and Christianity (Box 11)
        - Eighteenth Century Rationalism (Box 11)
        - Nineteenth Century Romanticism (Box 11)
        - Twentieth Century Secular Religions (Box 11)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
      - Correspondence and Corrections, 1970-1972 (Box 11)
      - Waveland Paperback edition correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 11)
    - The Human Animal
      - First edition, Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1954 (Box 11)
      - French edition, Paris: Payot, 1956 (Box 11)
      - The Fallen Ape (Version 1 of The Human Animal), 1950 (Box 11)
      - Family and Symbol: A Psychoanalytic Theory of Anthropology (Version 2 of The Human Animal), 1951 (Box 11)
      - The Human Animal: A Naturalistic Study of Man (Version 3 of The Human Animal), 1952 (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - Drafts (5 folders) (Box 11)
      - Correspondence, 1954-1963 (3 folders) (Box 11)
      - L'Animal Humain (French edition) correspondence, 1956 (Box 12)
      - The Human Animal (Italian edition) correspondence, 1979 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, circa 1990-1992 (Box 12)
      - Permissions and Legal Matters, 1953-1972 (Box 12)
    - Muelos: A Stone Age Superstition About Sexuality
      - First edition, New York: Columbia University Press, 1984 (Box 12)
      - Author's copy (Box 12)
      - Master copy (Box 12)
      - Corrected Original (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1985 (2 folders) (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 12)
    - The Peyote Cult
      - First edition, New Haven: Yale University Press, 1938 (Box 12)
      - Second edition, enlarged, The Shoe String Press, Inc., 1970 (Box 12)
      - Fifth edition, enlarged, Norman, OK: University of Oklahoma Press, 1989 (Box 12)
      - Spanish edition, El Culto Del Peyote, Mexico: Premia Editora, 1980 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1936-1956 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, circa 1949-1962 (Box 12)
      - Notes and Correspondence, circa 1979 (Box 12)
      - Oklahoma edition, notes and edits, circa 1988 (Box 12)
      - Xerox of Oklahoma edition and notes, circa 1988 (Box 12)
      - Oklahoma edition, notes and correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 12)
      - Survey of Peyote Studies, 1963-1973 (Box 12)
      - Spanish edition, correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 12)
      - Preface to 5th edition, 1989 (Box 12)
      - Miscellany (Box 12)
    - Shadow of Childhood: Neoteny and the Biology of Religion
      - First edition, Norman, OK: University of Oklahoma Press, 1991 (Box 12)
      - Edited manuscript (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - De Vos Lectures in Psychoanalytic Anthropology xerox, undated (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, 1989-1992 (2 folders (Box 13)
    - They Shall Take Up Serpents
      - First edition, Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 1962 (Box 13)
      - Paperback reissue, Waveland Press, Inc., 1992 (Box 13)
      - Early drafts (Box 13)
      - Manuscript, 1957 and undated (6 folders) (Box 13)
      - Corrected carbon, fifth version, Minnesota (2 folders) (Box 13)
      - Correspondence with rejecting publishers, 1956-1959 (Box 13)
      - Notes, correspondence, photos, circa 1948-1973 (Box 13)
      - Photographs, circa 1948 (Box 13)
      - Notes and correspondence, 1957-1961 (Box 13)
      - Editorial correspondence, 1959-1963, 1991 (Box 13)
      - Documents regarding Colonel Hartman Bunn (Robinson Everett), 1961 (Box 13)
      - Correspondence, circa 1991 (Box 13)
- Lectures and Addresses, 1936-1986
  The Lectures and Addresses series begins with a "List of Major Lectures" and a collection of 1960s-era programs and clippings. The bulk of the series, however, contains the text of La Barre's speeches, as well as correspondence and other materials related to the speech. The Lectures and Addresses series is arranged chronologically by the date each speech was given. Occasionally, La Barre gave the same speech over a number of years. In that case, folders are filed by their earliest date, but the date range of the folder contents are provided.
  - List of Major Lectures, 1946-1984, undated (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Programs and Clippings, circa 1960-1969 (Box 13)
  - Erotization of Body Parts in Various Cultures, Yale Anthropology Club, circa 1936-1937 (Box 13)
  - Alcoholism and the Psychopathology of Drinking Songs, Evening Staff Meeting, Menninger Clinic, circa 1938-1939 (Box 13)
  - Education and Democracy, Institute for Social Caseworkers, University of Wisconsin, August 1947 (Box 13)
  - Religion and Psychiatry, Topeka, circa 1939 (Box 13)
  - Some Observations on Japanese Character Structure, circa 1943 (Box 13)
  - Man as Animal Speeches, circa 1948 (Box 13)
  - A Comparative Look at Marriage, 13th Annual Groves Conference on Conservation of Marriage and the Family, April 24, 1950-April 26, 1950 (Box 14)
  - An Anthropologist Looks at the Family, Atlanta, Georgia, February 9, 1951 (Box 14)
  - How Cultural Patterns Influence People, Tampa, Florida, May 8, 1952 (Box 14)
  - Predicaments of Modern Men, Chattanooga, March 18, 1953 (Box 14)
  - Family in American Life, Kalamazoo, April 6, 1954 (Box 14)
  - Human Ecology Lectures: Human Biology and Human Culture, UNC Medical School, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Human Biology and Human Nature, Purdue, February 8, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Why Parents Don't Understand Their Children, Cornelian Corner lecture, Detroit, November 4, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Changing Attitudes toward Older People in Ancient and Primitive Societies, February 7, 1956 (Box 14)
  - Croatan and Robeson Indians, circa 1956-1957 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Mental Health, Detroit, March 14, 1957 (Box 14)
  - Social Work as a Factor in Producing Change, National Conference for Social Welfare, Philadelphia, May 20, 1957 (Box 14)
  - Washington-Baltimore Institute Speech, October 25, 1957 (Box 14)
  - Dartmouth Medical School, 1957 (Box 14)
  - A Naturalistic Approach to the Study of Religion, American Anthropological Association, Chicago, 1957 (Box 14)
  - And They Shall Take Up Serpents, Roheim Lecture, New York, December 4, 1958 (Box 14)
  - Cultural Methods of Dealing with Anxiety, Kalamazoo, circa 1958 (Box 14)
  - Indianapolis, March 26, 1959-March 27, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Time, Culture, and Style, New Orleans, June 21, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Adolescence and Anthropology, Child Study Association of America, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Pittsburgh Institute, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Method in Culture and Personality Studies, Lansing, Michigan, November 2, 1959-November 3, 1959 (Box 14)
  - The Changing Fabric of American Life, Texas Social Welfare Association, Houston, Texas, November 15, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Pittsburgh speeches, 1960 (Box 14)
  - Los Angeles-San Francisco, March 30, 1960-April 6, 1960 (Box 14)
  - Self Respect and Mental Maturation, Virginia Council on Social Welfare, Roanoke, April 27, 1961 (Box 14)
  - Parent-Children Relationships, Family and Child Service, Erie, Pennsylvania, May 1, 1961 (Box 14)
  - Millsaps College, Jackson, Mississippi, May 7, 1961-May 12, 1961 (Box 14)
  - A General Theory of Deculturation and Mass Autism, American Anthropological Association, Philadelphia, November 16, 1961 (Box 14)
  - School of Social Work, William and Mary College, Richmond, Virginia, December 1961-January 1962 (Box 14)
  - Architecture, Anthropology, and City Planning, Institute of Government, February 2, 1962 (Box 14)
  - The Family: Foundation of Social Forms, Associated Family and Child Service Agency, Winston-Salem, March 12, 1962 (Box 14)
  - Grand Tour, Spring 1962 (Box 14)
  - Indianapolis trip, May 1962 (Box 14)
  - Gainesville, Florida, October 9, 1963-October 12, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Bucknell University, November 4, 1963 (Box 14)
  - National Junior Science and Humanities Symposium, Washington, DC, April 23, 1964 (Box 14)
  - Culture, Charisma, and Culture Hero, Seventh InternationalCongress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences, Moscow, August 3, 1964-August 10, 1964 (Box 14)
  - The Pronoun God and the Soul as Hot Air, Indiana Lecture, November 8, 1964 (Box 14)
  - March 1965-August 1965 (Box 14)
  - National Science Foundation lectures, East Carolina University, Greenville, NC, Kalamazoo, April 1, 1965-April 2, 1965 (Box 14)
  - The Search for Pattern, Michigan State and Upjohn, East Lansing, Michigan, June 5, 1965 (Box 14)
  - University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, April 1966 (Box 14)
  - Columbus, OH, November 19, 1967-November 22, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Florence Crittendon Association of America, Wilmington, Delaware, October 10, 1968 (Box 14)
  - The Snake-Handling Sect of the Southeast, Kalamazoo, January 11, 1969 (Box 14)
  - Family in American Life, Kalamazoo, April 6, 1954 (Box 14)
  - American College of Psychiatry, New Orleans, January 30, 1969-February 2, 1969 (Box 14)
  - Hoffmann-La Roche Lecture, Nova Scotia, June 25, 1969-June 27, 1969 (Box 14)
  - Dallas, September 11, 1969 (Box 14)
  - How and Why History Happens, Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Texas, March 18, 1970 (Box 14)
  - Albuquerque-Los Angeles-San Francisco-Philadelphia-New York-Madison-Washington, April 3, 1970-April 14, 1970 (Box 14)
  - Authority, Culture, Change, and the Courts, Fifth Circuit Court,, Hollywood, Florida, May 26, 1970-May 29, 1970 (Box 14)
  - Piedmont Universities, December 6, 1971-December 8, 1971 (Box 14)
  - Simmel-Fenichel Lectures, Los Angeles, November 15, 1973-November 16, 1973 (Box 14)
  - Earlham College, February 21, 1974 (Box 14)
  - West Carolina University, April 24, 1975 (Box 14)
  - Bemrose-La Barre program Ideas, Toronto, Canada, November 1975 (Box 14)
  - Psychoanalysis and the Biology of Religion, American Anthropological Association, Washington, DC, 1976 (Box 14)
  - The Nature of Human Nature: An Anthropological Interpretation, Lynchburg College Senior Symposium, February 8, 1977 (Box 14)
  - Changing Attitudes in Primitive and Ancient Societies, Cumberland County Senior Roundtable, Fayetteville, NC, September 15, 1977 (Box 14)
  - The Human Animal Revisited with Some Remarks on Snakehandling, Earlham College, November 2, 1977 (Box 14)
  - De Vos Lectures, Berkeley, California, 1986 (Box 14)
  - De Vos Lectures, Correspondence, March 20, 1986-March 27, 1986 (Box 14)
  - Human Biology and the Supernatural, circa 1986 (Box 14)
- Professional Activities, 1935-1982
  La Barre had many interests in the field of anthropology and psychology, and was involved in committee and conference work throughout his career. This series contains four subseries: Committees, Conferences, Landmarks in Anthropology, and Research. The Committees and Conferences subseries are arranged alphabetically. The Landmarks in Anthropology subseries contains records from La Barre's editorship of the Landmarks in Anthropology series, which reprinted important anthropologial writings. The Research subseries has some information on grants and fellowships that La Barre received, as well as two folders of photographs which date from the mid-to-late 1930s and early 1940s. All of La Barre's field notes were donated to the Smithsonian Institution's National Anthropological Collection before La Barre donated the rest of his materials to Duke University.
  - Committees (Box 14)
    - American Orthopsychiatric Association Committee on the Problems of Minority Groups, 1960-1961 (Box 14)
    - Editorial Advisory Board of Law and Contemporary Problems, 1958-1959 (Box 14)
    - Geriatrics Research, 1954-1956 (Box 14)
    - Group for the Advancement of Psychiatry (GAP)
      - "Adolescence and Authority" Report, 1966-1972 (Box 14)
      - "Adolescence and Authority" Report, undated (Box 14)
      - Committee on Adolescence, 1960-1962 (Box 15)
      - Committee on Adolescence, 1962-1969, undated (Box 15)
    - National Institutes of Mental Health, 1958 (Box 15)
    - National Science Foundation Graduate Fellowship Panels
      - 1957-1958 (Box 15)
      - 1960-1963 (Box 15)
  - Conferences
    - American Anthropological Association
      - New Orleans, 1973 (Box 15)
      - Mexico City, 1974 (Box 15)
      - San Francisco, 1975 (Box 15)
    - American Psychoanalytic Association, 1977 (Box 15)
    - Hallucinogens in Native American Shamanism and Modern Life, 1978, undated (Box 15)
    - Meeting of the Study Group on Normal Humans of the American College of Neuropsychopharmacology, 1970 (Box 15)
    - San Francisco Psychoanalytic Society, March 1978 (Box 15)
    - Smithsonian Drug Conference, 1972 (Box 15)
    - Social Security Administration Meeting, 1960 (Box 15)
    - Yale Conference on Bolivia, 1942 (Box 15)
    - Young Presidents' Organization, 1972 (Box 15)
  - Landmarks in Anthropology
    - Correspondence
      - 1963-1965 (Box 15)
      - 1966-1968 (Box 15)
      - 1969-1971 (Box 15)
    - Series information (Box 15)
  - Research
    - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1946-1947 (Box 15)
    - Kiowa Indians field trip photographs, June 1935-August 1935 (Box 15)
    - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1946-1947 (Box 15)
    - National Science Foundation grants, 1962-1966 (Box 15)
    - Rockefeller Foundation grant, 1982 (Box 15)
- Duke University, circa 1948-1979
  The Duke University series contains materials related to La Barre's teaching career, participation in the faculty and administration of the Anthropology Department, and his interest in the Nixon Presidential Library controversy. The Teaching subseries contains quizzes, exams, syllabi, and other documents that La Barre used in teaching anthropology courses at Duke. It also contains information about him becoming a James B. Duke Professor, and a retirement letter he sent to all of his former students, as well as their replies. The Anthropology Department subseries contains information about staff meetings, department courses, and general administrative information. The Nixon Controversy subseries includes a scrapbook of clippings gathered during the debate over whether to place Nixon's Presidential Library at Duke. It also contains a memoir of personal recollections of that time written by La Barre.
  - Teaching (Box 15)
    - Anthropology Final Exams--Study Copies (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Anthropology Quizzes (Box 15)
    - Archeology, Prehistory, and Paleontology (Box 15)
    - Cultural Anthropology (Box 15)
    - Culture and Personality (Box 15)
    - Examinations, study guides, and other materials (Box 15)
    - General Anthropology (Box 15)
    - Human Biology and Physical Anthropology (Box 15)
    - James B. Duke Professorship, 1969-1970 (Box 15)
    - Linguistics (Box 15)
    - Marriage and the Family Quizzes (Box 15)
    - Peoples of the World - Miscellany (Box 15)
    - Primitive Art (Box 15)
    - Primitive Music (Box 15)
    - Primitive Religion (Box 15)
    - Quizzes in General Anthropology (Box 16)
    - Retirement letter to former students, 1976-1978 (Box 16)
    - Selected Examinations and Quizzes in Anthropology (Box 16)
  - Anthropology Department
    - General Files, 1959-1964 (Box 16)
    - General Files, 1965-1970 (Box 16)
    - General Files, 1971-1975, undated (Box 16)
    - Brochures, circa 1960-1979 (Box 16)
    - Courses, 1948-1976 (Box 16)
    - Staff Meetings
      - 1946-1967 (Box 16)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 16)
      - 1970-1975 (Box 16)
    - Visiting Lecturers' Announcements circa 1967-1976 (Box 16)
  - Nixon Controversy (Box 21)
    - La Barre Memoir (Box 21)
    - Newspaper History of the Proposal to Bring the Nixon Library Papers to Duke University (Box 21)
- Audio Recordings
  The Audio Recordings series is a small collection of what appear to be homemade recordings of music and lectures about anthropological topics. All of the recordings were made on 1/4 inch audio tape on 7 inch reels, and appear to be the master copies. Listening copies must be made prior to use; please contact University Archives for more information.
  - Baluba Tribe Music (Box 16)
  - Folk Music and Psychiatry (Drs. Spradlin and Mallory); Reverse: Labarre on Folktales and Limericks (Box 16)
  - Narcotics Lecture #1 (Box 16)
  - Narcotics Lecture #2 (Box 16)
  - Primitive Music #1 (Box 16)
  - Primitive Music #2 (Box 16)
  - S.F. State: Human Biology (Box 16)
  - Worm in the Honeysuckle, 1961 (Box 16)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series includes a variety of scrapbooks created by LaBarre. Some of the scrapbooks were collections of clippings saved by La Barre due to their anthropological or psychological interest. Some of the scrapbooks, including the "Ceylon," "Navy," and "China-India" volumes date from La Barre's service in World War II, and contain a number of original photographs. Other scrapbooks seem to be travel diaries, and include handwritten notes, ticket stubs, photographs, clippings, and other materials collected on his journies. La Barre also collected reviews and advertisements about his own books, and these materials were also pasted into scrapbooks. For this series, those books that had a title or obvious theme have been identified as such; those books that appeared to be a mix of subjects are classified as "Untitled."
  - Navy-era diary and notes, circa 1942-1945 (Box 17)
  - Europe travel diaries (3) (Box 17)
  - "Psychiatry Notebook" (containing clippings) (Box 17)
  - Italy and Greece travel scrapbook (Box 17)
  - Greece, Israel, and Western Europe travel scrapbook (Box 17)
  - "'Anthropologists,' collected by La Barre" scrapbook (containing clippings) (Box 17)
  - "Weston La Barre" scrapbook (containing clippings and reprints by and about La Barre) (Box 17)
  - "Weston's European Trips" (Box 18)
  - "Ceylon" scrapbook (containing clippings, photographs, and souvenirs) (Box 18)
  - "Navy" scrapbook (containing clippings, photographs, and souvenirs) (Box 18)
  - "China-India" scrapbook (containing clippings, photographs, and souvenirs) (Box 18)
  - "Collections Made by Weston La Barre" scrapbook (inventory of artifacts and artwork) (Box 18)
  - La Barre books scrapbooks
    - Culture in Context (Box 18)
    - Ghost Dance (Box 18)
    - Ghost Dance, Volume II (Box 18)
    - Human Animal (Box 18)
    - Human Animal/They Shall Take Up Serpents (Box 18)
    - Muelos (Box 18)
    - Shadow of Childhood (Box 19)
    - They Shall Take Up Serpents (Box 19)
  - 5 untitled scrapbooks (Box 19)
  - 7 untitled scrapbooks (Box 20)